Guide to the History of Medicine Picture File, 1523-2002 and undated RL.00570
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- History of Medicine Picture File: Places Series, approx. 97 items
  - Duke Hospital?, black-and-white drawing of exterior approach, driveway, and entrance to building, after 1940, box size: 11.5 x 14.5 inches (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Emory University School of Medicine, color painting on a pamphlet for Coramine Ciba, circa 1936 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Foundling Hospital, London, color engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Jew's Hospital, London, color engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Johns Hopkins, black-and-white photographs of the hospital buildings, circa 1923 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    14 photographs ranging in sizes from 3x4 inches to 8x10 inches, includes photographs of old pathology building, operating room and the medical library. Some have notes inscribed on print.
  - "De universiteit van leiden" [Leiden University], 1610, reproduction, circa 1970s, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches; 4 items (Box 15, Folder 13)
    Four modern reproductions of engravings of the Leiden University operating theater (anatomisch theater), arms training arena (schermschool), library (bibliotek), and garden (hortus). With accompanying essay in Dutch.
  - Leiden University library, "Bibliotecae Lugduno-Batavae cum Pulpitis et Arcis Vera Ixnographia," modern print reproduction of black-and-white engraving, 1610, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Lettsom birthplace, black-and-white engraving from magazine supplement, with the caption, "Scene in the Island of Little Van Dyke, near Tortola, with the House in which Dr. Lettsom was born," undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - London Operating Theatre, black-and-white photograph printed on paper, 1903 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Massachusetts General Hospital, assorted black-and-white postcards offering various views of the hospital, undated, 12 items (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Medical College of Georgia, black-and-white engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - The Montreal General Hospital, black-and-white illustration, 1823 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Paris, "Prospectus / amphitheatri anatomici / constructi / regnante Ludovico Magno / cura et sumptibus societatis regiae chirurgorum parisiensium an. MDCXCIV /...Amphithéatre anatomique construit sous le régne de Louis le Grand... / Paris, 1694," modern black-and-white photograph of engraving (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Paris, "Prospectus / amphitheatri anatomici / constructi / regnante Ludovico Magno / cura et sumptibus societatis regiae chirurgorum parisiensium an. MDCXCIV /...Amphithéatre anatomique construit sous le régne de Louis le Grand... / Paris, 1694," black-and-white engraving, 1694?, box size: 20x24 inches (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Pasteur Institute, black-and-white images, 3 items (Box 11, Folder 22)
    Includes two postcards, featuring the inoculation room and Pasteur's monument, and a picture of Pasteur's tomb, published in the Lancet.
  - Pennsylvania Hospital, southeast view, (original?) black-and-white engraving by John Exilius, who was a former patient there, mounted on board, 1814, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Includes note on provenance; states that 80 impressions were struck.
  - Philadelphia, negatives, undated, 5 items (Box 11, Folder 23)
    Title taken from original folder - subjects unknown.
  - Philadelphia Osler Memorial Building, pamphlet celebrating the dedication of the Osler Memorial Building, circa 1940 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Presbyterian Hospital, New York, black-and-white photo mechanical images from photographs, 1892, 3 items (Box 11, Folder 25)
    The East surgical male ward, the ambulance corps, and the children's ward are featured.
  - Walter Reed birthplace in Virginia, one black-and-white and two hand-colored photographs mounted on boards, circa 1927, 3 items (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Rochester, Minnesota, aerial view color postcard of Plummer Building, Mayo Clinic, after 1926 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Royal College of Physicians, black-and-white engraving, S. Wales, 1785 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Royal Hospital at Chelsea, color engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Royal Victoria Eye and Ear Hospital, Dublin, black-and-white engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Rush Medical College, color painting on a pamphlet for Lipoiodine Ciba, circa 1940 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - St. Bartholomew's Hospital, London, color engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Salpêtrière, copy of frontispiece from Iconographie photographique de la Salpêtrière, 1876-1877 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Saranac, N.Y., Adirondack Cottage Sanitorium, matted color print, undated, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Schenectady Free Dispensary, color painting on a pamphlet for Percorten, distributed by Ciba, circa 1939 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Trent Room in the Duke University Hospital Library, black-and-white photograph, color postcard, and 4 negatives, undated, 6 items (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Troy Hospital, color painting on a pamphlet for Dial, Ciba, 20th century (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Tufts College Medical School, color painting on a pamphlet for Perandren, Ciba, 20th century (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Universal Infirmary for Children, London, color engraving, undated (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - University of Padova, Palazzo Centrale, Teatro Anatomico di F. d'Acquapendente, 1594, 20th century black-and-white postcard and photographs of a Wellcome museum model, 1 postcard, 2 photographs, and 2 typed sheets on model specifications (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Vanderbilt University, color painting on a pamphlet for Percorten, Ciba, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Virginia Chimborazo Hospital, black-and-white illustration (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - Washington University, color painting on a pamphlet for Trasentin, Ciba, circa 1939 (Box 11, Folder 42)
  - Watkins Glen, NY, H.H. Babcock Company and front of building, 2x3" black-and-white photographs, undated, 3 items (Box 11, Folder 43)
  - Wayne University, color painting on a pamphlet for Coramine, Ciba, undated (Box 11, Folder 44)
  - Women's Medical College of Pennsylvania, color painting on a pamphlet for Lipoiodine, Ciba, undated, 2 items (Box 11, Folder 45)
    The second item is the historical note that has become detached from pamphlet.
  - Yale University School of Medicine Yale Medical Library, black-and-white postcards, undated, 4 items (Box 11, Folder 46)
    Subjects include the rotunda, a Connecticut pharmacy, and a reading room.
  - Yellow Sulphur Springs, Montgomery County, Virginia, color lithograph by Ed Beyer, from "Album of Virginia," 1857, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches (Box 17, Folder 4)
- History of Medicine Picture File: Subjects Series, approx. 487 items
  Series contains images, chiefly engravings and lithographs, of various practices, events, and themes related to the history of medicine. Arranged in alphabetical order by subject, and by box number within. The series is arranged by original topical groupings designated by library staff; new groups were also added for additions to the collection. The current divisions are: Advertisements; Anatomy; Apothecary Jars; Baths; Bindings; Bloodletting; Books and Illustrations; Buildings; Cardiology; Caricature; Cartoons; Cemeteries; Chemistry; Childbirth; Circumcision; Embryology; History of Medicine; Hospitals; Infant Care; Leeches; Manikins; Medical Costumes; Medical Devices; Medicine Chests; Military Medicine; Natural Science; Nurses and Nursing; Operating Rooms; Pediatrics; Pharmacies, Pharmaceutical; Physicians; Postcards; Psychology and Morality; Surgery; Surgical Instruments; Tourniquets; Trent Collection; Urine; and X-Rays. The largest series are Anatomy, Caricatures, Physicians, and Surgery.
  As with other series, the predominant formats are engravings and other printed items (including postcards, posters, broadsides, and clippings), and 20th century photographic images, often reproductions of printed works. Images are also often accompanied by a slide or negative reproduction created by Medical Library staff as far back as the 1960s. Sizes range from small prints under 10x12 inches, to oversize items of up to 23x30 inches. The dimensions of oversize boxes are given in the container inventory.
  - Advertisements, 20 items
    - Advertising cards for pharmaceutical products, 20th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches; 9 items (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Lederle's "Bulletin," pharmaceutical advertisements illustrated with scenes from history of medicine, circa 1950s, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 19, Folder 12)
      Nine large supplements with advertisements for antibiotics featuring lavishly colored illustrations of scenes from medical history across the centuries.
    - "Legacy of a lifetime: the medical illustrations of Frank H. Netter, MD, October 6-December 31, 2001, Health Sciences Library at University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill," poster, 2001, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - "Moore's throat & lung lozenges - the favorites," New York advertisement, lithograph, late 19th century, color reproduction, 20th century, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Anatomy, 92 items
    - Ne mala dissolvant molem solvisse jvuabit, black-and-white engraving by Pietro da Cortona (1596-1669), 1741, 5x7 inches (Box 12, Folder 1)
      There is a note on the item that indicates the illustration is from the title page of Berettini's Tabulae anatomicae, Rome. Engraving depicts two statues beside a fireplace, above which is a painting of an anatomical figure.
    - Human skeleton lying prostrate on table, reproduction of black-and-white engraving, undated, 5.75 x 9.5 inches (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Anatomia del corpo humano [two anatomical figures, one lying down, the other standing over him as if demonstrating cadaver dissection], Juan Valverde, photograph of engraving, Rome, 1560, 2 copies (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Anatomical drawing of human nervous system, by Dr. R.B. Weaver, film negative, 1868 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Races humaines, Dict. Univ. D'Hist. Nat., undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
      One plate with six water-color illustrations of differing racial skin types, by Werner.
    - Color opthalmology lithographic plates mounted on cards, Augenärztliche Unterrichtstafeln, Heft XI., Wintersteiner, Staare, Hugo Magnus (1842-1907), 19th century, 12 items (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Mostly illustrations of cataracts. Seems to also include several plates illustrating the typhus bacterium (typhoid).
    - Bronze "Écorché," anatomical model (statue) of human musculature, undated, 10 items (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Five black-and-white photographs, large and small, of statue; sizes vary from 2x4 to 8x10 inches; also includes five negatives.
    - Ivory skeleton, elbow resting on table, looking down, royal regalia spread along ground, undated, 7 items (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Five black-and-white photographs in sizes varying from 2x4 to 5x7 inches; also includes two negatives.
    - Anatomical model (statue), black-and-white photograph, undated, 8 x 10 inches (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Slight variation of the other bronze "Écorché."
    - A painter's studio, reproduction of painting by Boilly [two girls in Empire dresses, painting from anatomical models], black-and-white photograph of painting, undated, 8 x 10 inches (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Mansur's anatomy, late 15th century, modern reproduction images, 34 items (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Note indicates that the Persian manuscript was written by Mansur ibn Muhammad ibn Ahmad ibn Yusaf ibn Ilyas circa AD 1396; seven black-and-white photographs and negatives of all the illustrations in the manuscript are included.
    - De humani corporis ossibus, by Petri Paaw, black-and-white modern photographs of frontispiece and illustrations, 17th century, 9 items (Box 12, Folder 5.1)
      Three 5x7-inch photographs; also includes six negatives.
    - Kiu siu Kagami / Uvendorum locorum Speculum / 灸所鑑による経穴図 [Japanese acupuncture chart] (Box 12, Folder 5.2)
      Reproduction black-and-white image measures 6 1/2 x 4 5/8 inches and is mounted on black card. Originally an illustration from The history of Japan: giving an account of the ancient and present state and government of the empire, of its temples, places, castles and other buildings, of its metals, minerals, trees, plants, animals, birds and fishes... 2 vols., by Englebert Kaempfer, 1651-1716.
    - Manuscript drawings on one sheet of musculature of legs, ink, probably 18th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Corp. Humani Lib. I, 15. Hand-drawn ink figure of human skeleton, with labels, 17th century?, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 19, Folder 13)
      On retro, "De dissect. Partium. Eorum quae iacent humi in figure superiore per suas notas explicatio." Possibly created by medical student or for textbook.
    - Tibetan anatomical chart, print reproduction, undated, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 19, Folder 13)
      Large page torn out of German publication.
    - Human skeleton, black-and-white engraving, probably 19th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 19, Folder 13)
      Frontal and dorsal views, labeled with numerals (no key), on card stock.
    - Human musculature, 2 black-and-white engravings, Philadelphia, probably 19th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches; 2 items (Box 19, Folder 13)
      Four full-figure views of front and back, on card stock.
    - Anatomy drawings of the brain, black-and-white photographic reproductions, circa late 18th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches; 7 items (Box 19, Folder 14)
      Seven photos; each figure is mounted on card stock.
    - Human anatomy, engraving, 18th century?, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 15)
      Three figures, frontal view: human skeleton, part of venous system, and musculature.
    - Orate ne intretis in tentationem [skeleton seen from behind kneeling at altar and praying], 1779, reproduction of black-and-white engraving, undated, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 15)
      Modern reproduction of work by artist Jacques Gamelin; related to U.S. Army Medical Library Exhibit of Anatomical Illustrations.
    - Anatomical plates by Bernhardt Albinus, 1747 [advertisements, 1969], (9 items); box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 16)
      Modern reproductions in folder published by Riker Labs, California, advertising Norflex, musculo-skeletal anti-spasmodic.
    - Anatomical standing figures with successive layers of musculature, reproductions of engravings, 17th century, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches; 14 items (Box 15, Folder 16)
      20th century reproductions taking the form of black-and-white postcard-size images, taped onto two long pieces of hinged board, reproducing 17th century anatomical figures standing before a rural landscape with towns. When put together, the cards form a continuous image of successively flayed human figures against a panoramic background.
    - Anatomy of the head - eyes, ears, brain: four historical views, 1698-1818, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches; 4 items (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Four loose large black-and-white modern reproductions of engravings by Bartisch (1583), John Browne (1698), Le Cat (1744), and Soemmering (1818), published by Verlag.
    - Illustrations of the human body, New York, 1857, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Large chart, in color, with illustrations of the human musculature, organs, joints, and other parts; with advertisements for "olive tar" and for the J.R. Stafford's family receipt book.
    - Human skeleton with musculature, untitled color engraving, 1800s, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Large chart with hand-written annotations in French.
    - Wong's app [?] atlas of master acupuncture points, 1975, box size: 23 x 30 inches; 3 sheets (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Color prints, one for each view: frontal, side, and back. Includes lists for master points, angles of insertion, and code of meridians.
    - Anatomical drawing of ape skeleton (gorilla?), Japanese or Chinese, pen and ink on rice paper, undated, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Paper is very thin and transparent - handle carefully.
    - Anatomical drawing of human musculature, Japanese or Chinese, black-and-white ink and pencil on rice paper, undated, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Paper is very thin and transparent - handle with care.
    - "Universal artery situated nearly where Paracentesis is performed..." with key to sites, drawing, circa 1783, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Note on back of paper mount: "found in Monro, Observations on...nervous system, 1783"
  - Apothecary Jars, 24 items
    - Apothecary jars, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Ten color photographs and negatives.
    - Majolica pharmacy jars, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Color slides of 15th-16th century majolica jars from the Duke-Semans Fine Arts Foundation, for a 1991 exhibit.
    - Apothecary jar label, 18th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Armorial label (plate: 52x60 mm), to be cut out and pasted onto a jar; countermark "I & L Caprony, produced for Grenier, whose shop was near Lausanne.
  - Baths, 2 items
    - "Deutsches Badewasen in vergangenen Tagen," [bathing in current day] Alfred Martin, 1906 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      Pages from 1906 book, with four illustrations of different bathing scenes.
    - "Bildersammlung aus der Geschicte der Medizin," Georg Thieme, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Page from book, includes illustration of Das Manssfelderisch Schweiss Bad, 1622.
  - Bindings, 1 item
    - Historia Corporis Humani, Benedetti, 1527, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Bloodletting, 3 items
    - Barber-surgeon's establishment; a man is being shaved in foreground, while a man is being bled into a bowl in the background, engraving, 1800 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Bloodletting - knives and a sharpener, modern black-and-white photograph, 2 copies (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Books and Illustrations, 10 items
    - Engraving illustrating scribe at desk, black-and-white photograph, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Plate from book illustrating book-wheels, one photograph and one copper-plate (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Institutionum anatomicarum fecundu Galeni sententiam, 1536, modern black-and-white photograph of title cover (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Travels from lower Vienna, Richard Bright, title cover, 1814, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 10)
      A Journey to Morocco is placed in background.
    - The natural history of the sperm whale, Thomas Beale, title cover, 1839, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Journey from Moscow to Constantinople, William Macmichael, black-and-white photograph of title cover, 1819 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Runner equipped with an apparatus to register his different paces, engraving, 19th century, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - "White's Treatise," mechanical bed, engraving, 19th century, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Engraving of Messrs. Cruncher and son, 19th century, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - "La maladie," black-and-white engraving on card stock, Paris, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Vignettes of the stages of a man's life. The most prominent is an older man seated at his desk surrounded by books and chemical apparatus. A skeleton leans over his shoulder. Drawn by Nanteuil; engraved by Colin.
    - Poster of cover of book by/about Vesalius, by "Jeremy M," circa 2002 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Buildings, 1 item
    - "Photo used for dedication program, May 1976" [black and white photo of stairwell as abstract spiral, unidentified building or location], box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Cardiology, 2 items
    - "Heart murmur," by P. Hoffman, color etching, early half of 20th century, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 15, Folder 17)
      Shows physician bending with his ear to the back of a half-nude woman on bed to listen to her heart, disapproving older woman in background.
    - "Evolution of our knowledge of the heart and its diseases," black-and-white chart with milestones and advances in cardiology, mounted on board, 1938, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Caricatures, 26 items
    Caricatures, chiefly engravings and lithographs, of notable scientists and physicians (such as Pierre and Marie Curie, Sir William Jenner, Louis Pasteur) drawn by famous caricaturists of the day - Ape, Imp, Spy, and others. Other caricatures consist of scenes featuring some aspect of medicinal practice, including the use of nitrous oxide.
    - "Dr. Monsey," black-and-white engraving, Forster, published in European Magazine, 1789 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - "Surgery," Sir James Paget, Men of the Day no. 122, small print reproduction of illustration by Spy, Vanity Fair, 1876 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Consilium medicum, black-and-white engraving of men debating around a table, F. Geyer, 19th century (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Consilium medicum, with the supra-title, Kunstbeilage zum Riedel-Archiv, black-and-white engraving of men debating around a table, F. Geyer, 19th century, modern reproduction (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - "Dr. Syntax and his wife making an experiment in pneumatics," color photographic reproduction of print by Thomas Rowlandson, London, England, 1820 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      From an illustrated series, "Dr Syntax in Paris; or a tour in the Search of the Grotesque; being a Humorous delineation of the Pleasures and Miseries of the French metropolis," by William Combe (1742-1823). The reproduction, probably produced by the Medical Center Library, is accompanied by two pages of typed notes for a history of anesthesia slide lecture, faculty member name unknown.
    - "The company of undertakers..." [physicians with various implements], English, 18th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Was accompanied by card with note that gives the source as The Works of William Hogarth from the Original Plates, published by John Nichols, FSA, London, 1822.
    - "Physic," Sir William Jenner, Men of the Day No. 62, by Spy, Vanity Fair, 1873, 3 copies; box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - :"Hydrophobia," Louis Pasteur holding a rabbit, Vanity Fair, 1887 January 8, by "T", box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Scientific research! new discoveries in pneumaticks! or an experimental lecture on the powers of air [laboratory classroom at a "Royal Institute," with large audience of men and women watching three physicians experimenting with gases, with flatulent effects], color engraving, 1802, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Set of reproductions of 19th century caricatures of well-known scientists such as Darwin, Huxley, etc., with accompanying biographies, circa 1940s, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Set of nine color matted reproductions. Most of the original works are by "Spy." Distributed by pharmaceutical company Petrolagar Laboratories.
    - The reward of cruelty, "designed by W. Hogarth," 1751 [engraving of medical dissection of criminal's cadaver], box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "Radium," color lithograph of Marie and Pierre Curie by Julius Mendes Price ("JMP"), Vanity Fair, 1904, box size: 16x20 inches; 2 copies, one matted (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "Radium," color lithograph of Marie and Pierre Curie by Julius Mendes Price ("JMP"), Vanity Fair, matted, 1904, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Other copies located in box 16.